Hello friends. Welcome back to True
Health
Tuesdays. I am still new at this, so I'm
kind of awkward. You have to forgive me
if I'm not 100% as professional as uh
Pastor Ivor and Atante, but I'm I'm
learning. I'm learning. I'm I'm I'm
getting there. Uh but uh welcome back
to our health program. And uh today, as
you might already know, we're doing part
two of our program about cancer. So, if
you haven't watched the first part, I
hope you can watch the first one. You
don't have to do it now. You can do it
later. You know, it's in our on our
website um for Living Mana Church. I
think Power of the Lamb, I think True
Health Tuesdays has its own website now.
So, go ahead and watch it. I hope
sometime you can you know get caught up
with that because in the first part as
you might remember we talked about the
causes of cancer. And so now today we're
going to talk about well what we can
eat, what we can do to fight cancer. Of
course there's other things than just
food but you know one of my specialties
I guess my biggest specialty is
nutrition and I love to talk about food.
So today I'm going to talk about what
foods specifically uh fight
cancer. And so first of all, just like
last time, I'm going to tell you that
this uh program is not meant to be a
treatment for anybody. It's not meant to
diagnose anybody. This is 100%
educational. So if you have cancer or if
you know anybody who has cancer, make
sure you talk to a doctor. you're under,
you know, uh the uh care of a medical
um professional. Um but this could be
very educational for you. So that's what
I want to let you know first. And
second, as always, I will always tell
you this that everything I hope
everything that I speak in this program
will be always in harmony with this is a
spiritual disclaimer especially for
seventh day. Those of you who are
Seventh Day Adventist, everything that I
say hopefully will be 100% harmony with
the Bible and the spirit of prophecy. So
everything the rule that I follow, as
you probably already know, if you've
heard me before, is Isaiah 8:20 and
hopefully most of you know this verse by
now. If not, uh you will learn it. Is to
the law and the testimony. if it's not
according to this. So, anything that you
hear whether it's about health or about
spiritual truths, uh if you hear
something that is not according to the
Bible and the testimony, meaning the
spirit of prophecy, if it's not
according to this, if there's something
that is uh weird, that it doesn't sound
right, there's probably no light in it.
And uh as I've told you before, oh by
the way uh I think I remember you
telling you this last time. We are
living in very difficult times, very
special times. And uh the reason is
because we are under war. And this verse
tells us about this. The dragon was
enraged uh with the woman. The woman is
the church. and went to make war um to
the uh went to make war with the rest of
her the rest of the church meaning us
those who keep the
commandments and have the testimony of
Jesus and as we know the test what's the
testimony of Jesus again the Bible tells
us oops I went too fast the testimony of
Jesus is the spirit of prophecy the
Bible the Bible gives us the answers uh
the Bible interprets itself and as I've
told you before the the books that I
always recommend there's always more
books obviously there's a lot of
writings but if you haven't read these
two books I recommend you go and read uh
councils on food and uh wait what's the
name again because I can't see it that
screen is too small councils on diet and
food and ministry of healing highly
recommended those are very good to start
with Okay. Uh also by the way what I
think is very very important is the
scientific evidence is of good
good quality. And so as you see in this
pyramid the bottom the bottom the bottom
of this pyramid is opinion. So whenever
you hear people online Facebook YouTube
whatever social media in general
internet and Dr. such and such says and
that's the only proof they have is very
low quality evidence. Higher evidence is
scientific evidence that actually is
peer-reviewed. In other words, that
other people have looked into it. Just
like the Bible says the testimony of two
or more. So if just one expert says it,
it's not enough. Biblically speaking,
it's only one person. The Bible says
testimony of two or more. peer review.
That's exactly what it is. So, it's
biblical if you think about it in those
terms. All right? So, when you if you
look at the top of this pyramid over
here, peer-reviewed metaanalysis, that
kind of thing is many people looking at
the same evidence and saying, "Yes, yes,
this is good. This is actually good
evidence." That's what it means. All
right?
And right
here, look at this quote from testim uh
from the uh spirit of prophecy. Look at
what it says. The knowledge of science
of all kinds is power. We are not
anti-science. And a practical knowledge
of science of human life is necessary in
order to glorify God in our bodies. So,
sorry if I'm repeating this for those of
you who have seen this before, but there
might be people who have not seen it.
That's why I think it's worth repeating.
Okay.
Okay. So, I'm going to skip this one. We
are going to talk about
cancer. Last week, we talked about the
causes of cancer. I gave a little bit of
my testimony of how horrible cancer
sometimes could be, especially if it
touches someone in your family. It's
touched my family many times. When it
was my husband, it was a lot worse than
it was when it was, you know, someone a
little bit more removed. Uh, but cancer
is a little bit more I think scarier
than other u diseases. And uh just as a
sort of a review, we talked about the
stages of cancer, the
initiation, the promotion. By the way, I
forgot to mention
progression. I don't think I defined it
last
time. Progression is when that tumor So
initiation, let me start over.
Initiation is when there's damage. Do
you remember when I we talked about this
last time? there's um sort of a damage
to the
DNA, the genetic material inside of
cells, whether it's from chemical
damage, radiation, even viruses like
COVID can cause damage to the DNA of
cells and uh but that's just
initiation when that cell starts to
replicate. So that cells becomes one
cell becomes two, two become four, four
become eight, eight 16 and so on. That's
uh the second stage and that's
promotion. And last week we talked a lot
about promotion and what can lead to
promotion but also what can maybe even
stop promotion. So if you haven't seen
that, go back and watch that video. But
progression, I didn't really define it.
Progression is when that tumor or cells
from that tumor get into the um blood
flow or even lymph flow um and get to
other parts of the body and instead of
being just um in one
organ have gone to other organs. And you
also might know this as by another term
called
metastasis. When the cancer has
metastasized, it has gone into that
third stage called
progression. And that is much harder of
course to deal with as you can imagine.
So this is what we talked about last
week. Uh we talked about how that again
these toxins in the environment
sometimes we cannot avoid them. We don't
know what in the environment could have
played a part in one particular case of
cancer. We don't know. That's the scary
part about really about cancer. Like
what is it that caused my particular
case of cancer? I can't I it's really
hard to know honestly unless it's
something like lung cancer and cigarette
smoking. Honestly, that maybe could be
more a direct cause and it's really
easier maybe to tell. But other than
that, it's much harder. We are exposed
to so many things throughout our lives.
We talked about some of the foods as you
might remember. Some of it was somewhat
surprising to maybe some of you that
watched the uh video last time because
we talked about for instance protein
uh and how higher uh amounts of protein
particular oh well animal protein
because we actually I mentioned how they
did the same exact uh the ex same exact
exper experiments or studies with the
same animals And the plant proteins from
soy from wheat did not cause the uh
effects that animal protein in
particular in the case of Dr. T. Colin
Campbell it was casein the protein from
milk that caused the proliferation of
cancer cells. And so you can see this uh
in this in this um graphic. So that's
what they found. One of the things they
found is that animal protein causes the
proliferation of cancer cells. Uh
there's other things. Oh, by the way, so
Dr. T. Colin Campbell says it's almost
like turning cancer on and off. You can
read that in the book, The China Study.
Um so, but then he also found in the
studies that that actually affected the
promotion, remember? Because every
single animal in those studies was given
in a way cancer because they were
exposed to a cancer initiator, if you
will, whether it was alpha toxin, which
is very toxic, very cancer-causing
toxin, or they were animals that had the
uh cancer-causing
virus and uh they were all exposed to
that. So, they were all initiated, if
you will, but not all of them develop
cancer. Therefore,
this variable in this case was the
animal protein was somehow affecting the
second stage which is promotion.
Okay, remember we also talked about how
animal well actually not animal protein
this case is red meat or processed meats
is actually considered a
carcinogen by
uh the WHO the World Health Organization
or this particular uh agency in the
World Health Organization. So it's
considered a carcinogen. I mean it is
what it is. All right, we talked about
that there's this particular
um chemical that is produced
uh when the red meat in particular any
meat actually when it's post when it's
put on a grill when you put any meat on
a
grill apart from the proteins in the in
the meat the grilling process produces
many car carcinogenic substances And I
gave you one example, benzo pyrene for
instance. And this study actually talks
about those carcinogens. And it talks
about benzopyrene. And I mentioned last
week uh last time that the the
equivalent of 600 cigarettes is present
in two pounds of grilled meat. So that's
pretty surprising. I think it was
surprising for some of you guys. And we
talked about acryomide.
I don't know if you remember but we
talked about that present in uh fried
foods in particular because they achieve
a very high temperature. So these are
starchy foods that are put in high
temperature and they form
acryommites. And I think the last thing
we talked about is TMAO and these are
formed in the gut. When we eat certain
kinds of foods and these are the kinds
of foods that when present in the mic uh
in the presence of microbiota they form
these metabolites
uh that then we are exposed to and can
cause cancer. So TMAO is another one and
uh we talked about cholesterol.
cholesterol. When we eat foods with
cholesterol, maybe they don't cause our
serum cholesterol, meaning the
cholesterol in our blood, to go up.
That's maybe those two are disconnected.
Blood cholesterol and dietary
cholesterol, maybe they're disconnected.
Okay, fine. But the dietary cholesterol
still causes
cancer because that's what they have
found. I'm just giving you a review of
last time. And to conclude last time's
re uh last time's uh program, we came to
this uh quote that I find fascinating.
The results of these and other studies
show that
nutrition nutrition is more important in
controlling
the there's that word again promotion of
cancer than the doses of cancer
initiators. So the conclusion that Dr.
Campbell came to is that yes, we can be
exposed to many chemicals, fertilizers
and all these different uh pesticides,
whatever chemicals and food. We can be
exposed to those things even in the food
we buy. We might not be able to afford
everything
organic, but that doesn't mean that
we're going to just give up and eat junk
from now on because we can't buy organic
fruit. No. Because actually the fruit
and the vegetables that are not organic,
you can wash them first of all. you can
clean them and take out 90 to 95% of
those fertilizers and those uh
pesticides, but those fruits and
vegetables inside also have these
magnificent compounds that I'm going to
talk to you about today that actually
fight
cancer and don't have those
cancer-causing things such as protein,
cholesterol, and these other things that
might cause cancer. Therefore, the
nutrition, what you
eat, what you're exposed to in the diet
might have even more
effect in the promotion of cancer than
that
original whatever you were exposed to,
toxin or ex, you know, ex uh excess UV
rays from the sun or whatever you were
exposed to, what you eat might be even
more important. And here's another quote
that we read last uh time. Cancer
promotion again that second part of that
development of cancer. Cancer promotion
he says is reversible. Remember when
when we read this and I was like I'm
glad I didn't say it because this is a
very bold
statement, very bold. I don't think any
medical uh doctor will be bold enough to
say it, right? Because this is kind of
going against the grain if you will,
against the conventional knowledge or
conventional wisdom, conventional, you
know, the conventional uh sayings right
now because most people will say, "Yeah,
cancer is incurable. You're just going
to use this treatment to keep it in
check. Hopefully, won't come
back." But here it says cancer promotion
is reversible. But not just
reversible, it depends. It depends on
what on whether that initial cancer
growth has the correct conditions to
grow. So when you were
exposed to whatever it is that's causing
cancer, that's the key. When you were
exposed to whatever that thing that
causes cancer, were the conditions in
your
body good for that cancer to grow or
were they not?
We don't know. But from now
on, do you want to have those conditions
in your body for cancer to
grow or do you
not? It's up to
you. It's up to you. And you know what?
Now I'm remembering that I took out some
slides that I totally wanted to show you
and I just remembered that I forgot to
put them. I'm just gonna tell you about
a study and you can look it up. In fact,
I'll just, you know, just send me, you
know, uh, oh, by the way, if you've
written me these last two weeks, I
apologize. I try to, uh, respond to
many, many messages. I did respond to,
many I did not have time to because I
have been doing the 10-day program at my
work right now. And it was a little bit
more difficult than usual because of the
holiday. The clinic we usually partnered
with was closed for the holiday. Uh they
always close for holidays, but we
usually partner with a church when the
clinic is closed, 7th Avenue Church in
Watsonville, California. And that church
is tearing down the building, the the
fellowship hall where we usually meet
when the clinic is closed. And so we
couldn't meet there either. and we
almost didn't have the
class and so we were looking
frenetically for a place to meet all of
last week and it was just terrible. We
almost had to class at class and I have
noticed that when we cancel the class
our results suffer we do not have the
same outcomes. That educational
component is very very important. People
need to know people need to know in
their brain why food is so important for
these diseases. when they don't hear it,
they don't have the same motivation. So,
I apologize if I haven't answered your
uh your messages that you've sent me in
my website. But if you do send me a
message these next few days, I will be
looking into those messages the next few
days. Sorry. But what I want to say is
that I could send you the uh references
for the study where what what happened
is this. They took um blood from women
who had
um who had breast cancer and they had
these uh petri dishes. I don't know if
you've seen if you've taken any like uh
biochemistry class or whatever. And so
they put these cancer cells in petri
dishes and they put the blood of these
women on those cancer cells.
And at first first before the
intervention, well, nothing happened.
The cancer cells were still there. And
then what they did, the intervention was
that they put these women on a plant uh
plant-based diet for two
weeks. And after the two weeks, they
repeated the um the experiment where
they put the blood on the cancer cells
and they looked at them again with a
microscope, obviously. And the second
time they did this after the
intervention, two weeks of a plant-based
diet, that blood destroyed those cancer
cells. And they actually show in the
study, and I wish I had put this slide.
I didn't I wish I had taken it out. They
actually show the difference before and
after. You see the two pictures. one
with the cancer cells before the
intervention where the blood did did
nothing. And the second
picture with no cancer cells. So the
blood of these women after two weeks of
eating a plant-based diet was able to
get rid of the cancer cells, which is
amazing. Another thing is uh a study
that Dr. Dean Ornish, you can look this
up, Dr. Dean Ornish is very famous for
having been one of the first who did a
study that found that uh coronary heart
disease can actually start to be
reversed. So before this in the 1990s
every doctor thought that once you had
coronary artery disease in other words
the accumulation of plaque inside your
arteries uh once that started to happen
it was irreversible.
But he in the early 1990s published a
study where they found that yeah, if you
put people on a plant-based diet, that
plaque that starts to uh obstruct those
arteries actually can start to go down,
become thinner, and in other words, the
obstruction starts to go away. And so he
became famous. But more recently, he did
a study with uh patients with prostate
cancer. And uh what they found is that
early stage prostate cancer, the uh men
who were put on a plant-based
diet, they actually uh got
better. Their numbers became better.
Their uh cancer did not progress. So
they put the group of men into two
separate groups. Some had the
intervention, some didn't. In the
intervention group, the cancer did
progress and some of them had to then be
put on a cancer treatment. Whereas the
men who did have the the uh
intervention, meaning the the uh
plant-based diet, none of them uh had to
be put on cancer treatment because none
of their none none of them had actually
a cancer that progressed. So, those are
very good studies of the possible good
outcomes of a plant-based diet on
cancer. So, that's pretty awesome, I
think. So, if you're interested, I can
absolutely send you um those studies if
you're interested in in the uh
references. So, what we're going to talk
about is well, what are these
foods? What foods are they that fight
cancer? You probably already have an
idea, but I'm about to talk to you about
specific things in the foods. What's in
the foods that fight cancer? Why should
you eat them? Okay, so the first thing I
want to talk to you about is
antioxidants. You probably heard that
word before, like antioxidants people
hear all the time in the media, right?
Or, I don't know, social media, right?
like doctor's
presentations videos, people talk about
antioxidants and it's a word that's used
all the time. But but what is it though?
I kind of want to tell you a little bit
what it is so at least you know because
it's a bit of
a concept that a lot of people might not
know really what it is and maybe this
will help you. Maybe it'll give you an
idea. I don't know if it will. if it
will help. But antioxidant like it says
in this um slide, antioxidants are
naturally occurring molecules that are
present in certain foods obviously that
help to fight free radicals. Ah, there's
another word like what are free
radicals? Well, it says right here, but
what do antioxidants do? They donate an
electron. Now, we're talking about chem
chemistry, but just just stick with me a
little bit, okay? Electrons. They donate
electrons
um so that they don't steal the
electrons from healthy cells. So, here's
a little bit of an illustration that I
added for you. Here's a healthy cell.
Here's a free radical. See, this is a
bad guy. The bad guy steals an electron
from a healthy cell. So, now it damages
Free radicals. Here's free radicals.
Here's the definition. Free radicals are
missing an electron. So what do they do?
They steal it from healthy cells, thus
causing damage. Okay? So here's the bad
guy. Stealing an electron from a healthy
cell. It damages these
cells. That's why free radicals are
bad. What do antioxidants do?
This is how they help. They donate the
electron to the free radical so they
don't have to go out and steal it from
the healthy cells. Okay, I hope that
helps. So that at least you know what's
happening. At least you know kind of the
big picture. Um there here's another
slide that maybe helps too. So
antioxidants are group of naturally
occurring substances that protect cells
from oxidative damage. I wanted to put
this also uh in the in the PowerPoint
presentation because oxidative damage is
another big word that people hear and I
don't know if everybody knows really
what it is. Oxidative damage. Well, what
is it? Well, it's o it's basically the
damage caused by these free radicals.
That's really what it is. So, here it is
again. oxid uh antioxidants are touted
uh to fight free radical damage by
donating electrons to
deactivate the free radical. So that's
what's happened here. He's talking about
in particular about uh protecting the
skin but not just protect it doesn't
just protect uh or antioxidant don't
just protect skin they do much more than
just protect skin they actually can uh
prevent cancer. So they prevent damage
as I said to cells. So they're very very
um they're very good for us. But I want
to give you uh one I want to tell you
one thing. They have done
studies with taking supplements of
antioxidants. When they discovered how
good antioxidants are, they actually
started doing studies by giving
supplements to people. And they found
that supplements do the exact opposite
as the foods with the antioxidants. They
actually found that when they I think it
was smokers, they gave vitamin A and
instead of preventing cancer from
developing in smokers, they actually
cause more cancer.
So, it's better to get them from food.
trying to get them from food, not from
taking pills. In other words, pills are
not from God. Foods are from God. So,
let's get our antioxidants from the
source, the original source, which is
the food that God made. All right?
So, what's the best source for
antioxidants? You probably already know
that fruits and vegetables.
actually fruits and vegetables that are
the most colorful. I always tell this,
you probably already heard it a million
times. Eat the rainbow. Why? Because the
more more colorful the fruits and
vegetables are, the more brilliant, the
more, you know, the the the colors that
are more uh darker, more colorful, you
know,
the just the more colorful the fruits
and vegetables are, the better because
that means they're there's more pigments
in these fruits and vegetables. And the
pigments are the
antioxidants. That's why we tell you to
eat the rainbow.
Now, you've probably already heard about
cruciferous vegetables. Amongst all
vegetables, cruciferous vegetables stand
out probably the most. You've probably
heard this. I hope you have because if
you've heard it, that means you're
paying attention. Cruciferous vegetables
have in particular this one compound
that you see on the screen called
sulfurophane. Have you heard about
sulfurophane? I hope you have. If you've
heard about
sulfurophane, you've probably heard
about it has so many so many benefits. I
don't have time to go over all the
benefits of
sulfurophane. I'm going to talk only in
uh relation to
cancer. But sulfurophane in relation to
cancer has been shown to prevent
cancer and number two
inhibit well they've done studies in
particular with breast cancer for
instance where they found that inhibits
breast cancer stem cells which are the
ones that then become u other types of
cells that's stem cells are so the
mechanisms what by which uh sulurophane
might have these effects
might be uh by inducing apoptosis. I
don't know if you've ever heard of this
word. Did I mention it last time? I
might have.
Apoptosis is basically the way in which
cells destroy themselves. They it's
programmed cell death. Uh so it's it's
it's a very good sort of system that
cells have to get you know die but it's
orderly death if you will. It's
programmed ahead of time. Uh so the uh
sulfurophane induces cancer cells to
die.
But also the other way in which
sulfurophane might act is by suppressing
I I'm pretty sure I mentioned this term
last time
angioenesis. Do you remember that word
last time?
Angioenesis meaning means the production
of blood vessels and blood vessels is
the production of blood vessels is great
unless it's in tumors because if you're
feeding the tumor with blood
vessels that means you're feeding the
tumor with blood meaning it's growing
more. You don't want androgenesis.
Anything that prevents angioenesis in
tumors is good because that means the
tumor is not
growing. So that's what
sulurophane does. It prevents
angioenesis in tumors. That's actually a
good
thing. Isn't that wonderful? All right.
So all cruciferous
vegetables have it, but broccoli in
particular is the highest. Did you know?
Did you know by the way that well I
won't tell you until I see that slide
but all what are the cruciferous
vegetables broccoli but all the cousins
of broccoli uh cabbage red cabbage has
more of not
just red cabbage has more of also other
antioxidants because of the u has more
pigments right because it's red but all
cabbage is good actually. So, eat it.
Uh, cauliflower of course is good. Do
you know these little things right here?
A lot of people don't like them. The
Brussels sprouts, you see them? Uh,
also, by the way, did you know that
these two green vegetables are also
cruciferous
vegetables? Do you guys eat them? the
green cruciferous
vegetables, green leafy vegetables, the
kale, the u color
greens. Do you eat them? Put a one in
the chat if you eat collar greens and
kale. There's many varieties of kale, by
the
way. So, I hope you're eating your your
green vegetables every
day. Why should you eat a green leafy
vegetables every day?
Why?
Why? Because green vegetables, green
leafy
vegetables are the
most nutrient-dense foods in the human
diet. What's
nutrient-dense? Meaning they have the
most amount. Oh, there's a one. There's
a one in the chat. Only one person. No,
I can't believe only one person. Oh,
there's another one. Great. Two people
eat greens. Three. Three people eat
greens every day. Ah, I feel better now.
All right.
Wonderful. As I was say, four.
Okay. Awesome. We have we have healthy
people. Yay.
As I was
saying, green leafy vegetables, you
guys, have the highest nutrient
density of any other food in the human
diet. Meaning they have the highest
concentration of micro nutrients per
weight. What are
micronutrients?
Vitamins,
minerals, phytochemicals.
So the all these other substances that
oh there's another one all these
substances that are fighting cancer and
heart disease and autoimmune diseases
and on and on and on and on. Okay, these
disease fighting
chemicals sounds kind of weird to say
chemicals because when we say chemicals
we think of bad things. These are good
substances. So, they're phytonutrients,
phytochemicals. Okay, they're not bad.
They're good. All right, so green leafy
vegetables every day. If you're not
eating your green leafy vegetables every
day, you can start today or you can
start tomorrow actually because it's
kind of late today, but maybe tomorrow.
You can eat them in a big salad or you
can steam them briefly. You don't need
to overcook them. You can make a green
smoothie. So many ways. All right. What
I was going to say before is that did
you know that broccoli sprouts have 10
times more sulforophane than regular
broccoli? Did you know up to 100 even?
Did you
know? No. Yes. No. Well, they do. So, if
you really want to get more sulforophane
in your life, in your
body, make some broccoli sprouts. Go to
the health food store or order them
online. These little
seeds and sprout them. How do you sprout
them? Soak them overnight. The next
morning, you put the the soak them
overnight in a jar like this glass jar.
put a little metal screen or whatever
other screen that you're like I don't
know like a cheesecloth I guess would
work uh so that can breathe also but it
can also drain and so soak them
overnight the next morning you let it
drain out well uh wash them before like
let the water drain out and
uh and then let the wa I guess you would
rinse them again and then let the water
drain out but put the jar like this on
an angle so it could be draining the
whole time. That's what I do. I always
have a jar of uh broccoli sprouts going
for my husband. Actually, I eat them
sometimes. I mostly make them. I have
one right now over there. I would go get
it, but then you know you'd be bored
while you wait for me. So, I won't bring
it. But I have one right now going takes
about And so, what do you do? Um, you
rinse it three times a day. That's what
I do. Rinse it three times a day. In
about 5 days, you get these little
sprouts that you see on the screen.
Question, should we eat leafy greens raw
or cooked? I'd say however you're going
to eat them. But if you eat them raw,
you probably get more nutrition out of
them. And if you're going to eat them
cooked, I would say steam them briefly,
maybe two or three minutes. I don't
think you need to do more than that. So,
you want to preserve the color as much
as possible. You would still want them
to be very bright green. If you cook
them for too long, you're probably going
to be destroying a lot of those um a lot
of those nutrients. All
right. Uh so, our producer, hope she's I
hope she's reading the uh the uh
comments. I can't control the size of
the screen. Our producer can do it. So,
we're being asked if it could be put on
full screen. So, oh yes, there it is.
Thank you, producer. Um, so there it is.
Broccoli sprouts. Awesome, you guys. So,
maybe you can do the other way. Me small
and the slight big. All right. Anyway,
let's talk about berries. Oh, berries
are just the bomb. Berries
for diabetics.
I recommend berries as the number one
fruit. You know why? There are studies
that have shown that not only do they
not elevate blood sugars, they actually
lower I would tell you all about if we
have time because I just talk too much.
I won't tell you all about it. I'll just
mention it that berries lower blood
sugar. They do not elevate they're
fruit. They have they're sweet but they
do not elevate blood sugars. They lower
blood
sugar. That's all I wanted to tell you.
Okay, in regards to that. But when it
comes
to
cancer, effects of berries are amazing.
First of all, they attenuate
inflammation. They lower inflammation.
They inhibit andioenesis. Did you
already forget what androenesis is or do
you still remember? I hope you still
remember. angiogenesis, the formation of
blood vessels in tumors. They inhibit
it, protect DNA damage. They protect DNA
damage. They have effects on apoptosis.
Did you already forget the word
apoptosis or do you still remember
apoptosis? Pro programmed cell deaths.
So, it makes uh tumor cells die
basically. Uh they also have observed
researchers that is they have observed
that berries extend their effects on the
proliferation rates of pre- listen
pre-malignant pre-malignant in other
words before cancer even becomes cancer.
Isn't that amazing?
uh not only berries uh help prevent
cancer but it has been shown that
consumption of other fruits and
vegetables obviously all fruits and
vegetables are associated with reduced
cancer mortality. So, I want you to not
just eat berries, okay? But I just
wanted to say that berries are number
one when it comes to amounts or
concentration of uh antioxidants.
They're the number one. But honestly,
all fruits and vegetables are
anti-cancer. So, do not leave the other
ones out. That's why they tell us how
many servings a day. Remember, fruits
and vegetables, how many? One, two,
three, four, five. At least. Do you know
that 98% of Americans do not eat five a
day?
98%. Makes me want to cry. And now even
the government says five a day is not
even enough. It should be six to
nine. How much is that? At least half a
pound. At least. Are you eating half a
pound of fruits and vegetables a
day? Are we? Because actually should be
about 600 grams. That's even more than
half a pound. So about 300 gram of
vegetables and 300 g of fruit a day
every single day. I hope I hope I
hope we are trying at least to eat that
much because they all fruits and
vegetables inhibit the proliferation of
cancer
cells. Cancer
cells. Here are some of the other ones
that are top of the list. Apples, red
grapes, bananas, grapefruits, peaches.
Do you like any of those? I sure hope
so. I like some of those. Aren't they
delicious? Fruits are great. They're
like the fast food made by
God. What do you need to do to fruit to
to uh make it taste good? Absolutely
nothing. They taste good already. They
don't have to cook it after that. Salt,
sugar, nothing. It's fast
food, isn't it? Made by
God. Okay. Now, we're going to talk
about
controversial. Are you ready? This is
going to be
controversial. Sorry, you guys. I need
to say it. It needs to be
said because this is uh Whoa. How can I
say it? This is controversial. That's
the word. Some people
um Well, here's the thing. There's been
misinformation. That's just the That's
the truth. There's been a lot of
misinformation. And you know
why I believe the misinformation?
Well, I have I pretty much know the
misinformation started because the food
industry started uh spreading the
misinformation about soy when soy became
really uh popular even back in the I
don't know 70s even when a lot of the
you know hippie crunchy granola people
started eating a lot of soy they wanted
to stop eating meat and it became really
uh it became really
popular. But even before that, honestly,
even before that, even in the 1960s, I
would say when the health um Adventist
health studies started to come out, the
first ones, it showed that uh Adventists
who ate back way back when, I mean, I'm
talking about like the 60s, Adventists
who were eating soy way back then were
having less cancer.
uh than people who didn't eat soy. And
the Adventists probably got the idea
from, I don't know, ancient Asian
cultures who've been eating soy since, I
don't know, 5,000 years ago. I don't
know, 2,000 years
minimum. And they have less cancer.
They've had less cancer this whole time.
Anyway, I'm just going to give you the
facts, okay? You can look it up.
But here's the thing, always, always,
always to the law and the
testimony. See who's who's telling you
all this
information. Who where's the source? Is
the source reliable? Because when I
first started doing these
presentations 20 years ago, not lately,
20 years ago, I looked at the original
source of the misinformation and it was
mostly
um people who were recommending at the
time eat a very highfat diet. It wasn't
the keto diet yet because keto diet
wasn't around. It was people who were
recommending eating
lard, eating, you know, uh, beef tallow,
all these other, you know, uh, source,
of course, meat, red meat a lot. I'm
like to the law the testimony. No, this
does not, this is not a good source of
information. So, try to apply that, too.
Okay? See who's recommending, you know,
not eating soy or whatever. Okay? So,
here's the thing. Why is it
controversial to eat soy? Mostly because
people talk about estrogen, right? Does
soy have
estrogen?
No. Soy has isoflavones that are
considered phyto remember the word phyto
means
plant. Phytoestrogens are plant
compounds that mimic the effects of
estrogen in the body.
and are as these phytoestrogens are
associated with a reduced risk of
colorctyl and breast
cancer. Now contrary to the myths that
circulate on social media networks on
the
internet, soy not only does not cause
cancer, hear me out, please just be
patient.
not only does not cause cancer, it
actually prevents it. The according to
studies of for example breast cancer
survivors, consumption of soy, just 10
milligrams of isoflavins a day was
associated with reduced cancer
recurrence in one study of breast
cancer.
There's studies that they have done with
soy where they showed 29% lower risk of
dying from breast cancer and 36% lower
risk of cancer recurrence. I remember a
lady uh this was maybe about 15 years
ago, another church that I used to go to
and she had had breast cancer and and
then she had treatment or whatever and
at our podlux she would say, "Oh, I
can't have that because uh I had breast
cancer. I can't eat soy. I can't eat
tofu."
misinformed because there's 36% lower
risk of cancer
recurrence if you eat soy. Now, I'm not
talking about soy burgers, highly
processed soy, I don't know, uh, hot
dogs or something. I'm talking about soy
in its less processed form. Now, soy
phytoestrogens activate the BA one and
the BA 2 genes. I don't know if you've
heard of these. These are anko
suppressor genes. What does that mean?
They suppress cancer development. These
are genes that suppress cancer
development. And some
people have this genetic predisposition
to cancer because they inherit there.
It's a
rare hereditary cancer because some
people have this uh
gene where it these bracket jeans aren't
working properly. So this is that's why
um that famous actress I forget her name
she had double mastctomy. What's her
name? Anyway you guys know put in the
chat for me because I remember I forgot
her name. I'm blanking out right now,
but people have this double mastctomy
when they think they're going to have
breast cancer because they lack the
brack one, Bracka 2 genes.
Well, phytoestrogens activate BA 1,
Bracka
2. Isn't that amazing? I don't know how
people know this. I have no
idea. So, this is why soy consumption
provides important
benefits because they activate the BA uh
these these ankosuppressor genes. Okay.
And so they they help people with
hereditary cancer and non-hereditary
cancer. So people who are worried about
the estrogen
thing, as I said last uh program,
estrogen or soy, I mean the soy
phytoestrogens are selective estrogen
receptor modulators. What does that
mean? They can generate positive effects
of estrogen in some tissues such as the
bone for example and then can have an
listen
anti-estrogenic effect in other tissues
such as breast cancer when
needed similar to some
drugs. So in other words, they can help
you uh pre you know like fight like have
the anti-estrogenic effect when needed
or pro-estrogenic effect when needed.
That's why it's
selective selective estrogenic receptor
modulators, positive
effects. Is that It's pretty amazing.
It's pretty amazing.
So, um, and there's a whole there's a
whole scientific explanation why they
are selective. It has to do with the
estrogen receptors alpha and beta.
There's a whole explanation. I'm not
going to go into it because it's long. I
just wanted to tell you that the women
with the highest soy isoflavin
uh intake like Asian women for example
who eat about one or two servings a
day usually in the form of tofu or soy
milk or whatever have the lowest risk
rate for cancer recurring
uh in
women. Ain't that amazing? lowest risk
of cancer rec recurrence about
half. Uh larger study in China was done
showed the same positive effect of
eating soy foods not supplements soy
foods and both hormone receptor positive
and hormone receptor negative cancers.
So all I can tell you is this is what
the researchers have found. Among women
with breast cancer consumption, soy food
was significantly associated with low
risk of death and cancer
recurrence. Okay. So if you hear
misinformation, try to ignore it. That's
all I can say. Try to ignore it. Here's
one study for instance that you can look
at the study. Take a picture of the
screen and then in your own time look it
up. Read the study. Just read
it. Okay.
But as I was saying, health adventist
study one. This was done. Okay. No, the
one I was mentioning before was the uh
Adventist mortality study that was done
in the 50s. That was the first uh health
adventist study, but it wasn't called
health adventist study one. It was
called the Adventist mortality study I
think it was called and that found
already decreased mortality. But the
health advent study one which was done
in the 70s in particular found that men
who drink soy milk more than once a day
can reduce the risk for prostate cancer.
Oh, Angelina Jolie, somebody put it.
Thank you. Thank you you guys. Angelina
Julie is the actress that took the
double mastctomy and it's because of
that rare form of hereditary cancer has
to do with the bracka one and bracka 2
genes that suppressors um or that the
yeah they're lacking those
genes all right as I was saying men
advent men who drink uh one or more um
or drink soy milk one or once or twice
or more a day I
reduce the risk of prostate cancer by
70%. That's quite significant.
70% is quite a bit. It is a lot. I think
I think
so. Here's another one. Uh people think,
"Oh, men can't have a soy." Oh, no, no,
no, no. That will interfere with their
uh masculinity, I guess, or the
fertility. Oh, no. They won't have
babies. Oh, yeah. Well, uh, people in
China eat a lot of soy and, uh, does it
interfere with their fertility? Has been
interfering with their fertility in the
last 100
years? Uh, I don't think so. It's the
most populated country in the world. So,
I don't think it's interfere with any
fertility. Just
saying. All right. Uh if you really want
to know all the myths, if you want to
dispel all the myths of
soy, this study is the biggest study
I've read or I have seen period. Not
just in soy. It's the biggest study I
have
seen ever on anything. It's a meta
analysis of 400 I I forgot how many
exactly, but 467 I think studies. It's a
huge study. is over 60 pages. It's the
biggest study I've ever seen on
anything. Uh it was done by Luminda I
think
researchers published in
2021 I
think. It's a really really big big
study. I highly recommend it if you
really want to go deep into it. And they
honestly go through every single thing
that people are worried about.
Cancer, thyroid
problems, hormonal imbalances, babies
that drink too much soy formula or
whatever. I don't know,
adolescents, boys, girls, whatever. All
of the issues with soy that you have
heard right and
left, they go through every single study
that has been done regarding that
particular
topic and they analyze them, every
single one and they come come to a
conclusion regarding that. And for the
most part, I can tell you the bottom
line is that they're not been
proven. Uh scientifically speaking, they
have not been proven. Most of the
studies, most of the scary studies have
been done with animals, not humans, with
amounts of soy that you would have to
eat a truckload of tofu to be able to
achieve those kinds of concentrations of
soy to get those kinds of effects. And
they're usually not even foods. They're
concentrates. They're not actually tofu
or, you know, soy beans or soy milk. No,
they're concentrated uh tofu or I mean
soy proteins or something. They're not
foods.
So, I don't know what else to say. These
myths have been debunked. That's the
bottom line. What else can I tell you?
If you have questions, put them in the
chat. If you have questions about soy,
but bottom line, soy beans and the
minimally processed soy foods that are
made from soybeans, you can make soy
milk at home. I just made it today. I
make soy milk myself in my house with a
soy milk maker that I bought. It's like
big thing like this. Mix it in about
half an hour. I have the pulp. I use
that pulp also. You can use the pulp to
make I add it to my oatmeal. Yummy. It's
good. Uh and then I drink the milk.
That's it. With that milk, you can make
tofu at home if you really want to take
the time. The fact that you can make it
at home indicates that tofu is a
minimally processed food. It's not a
highly processed food. If it was a
highly processed food, you would not be
able to make it at home. That's pretty
much the definition of a highly
processed food. You can't make it at
home. So, tofu is a minimally processed
food. All right? So, if you eat those
foods, you'll be good. By the way,
here's another thing that you probably
don't know. Okay? Did you know that
flax, what you're seeing on the screen,
flax food, everybody loves to talk about
flax. Flax and chia, by the way, are
very similar. They both have what what
are called the omega-3 fatty acids.
They're very anti-inflammatory as you
probably know. They're awesome, right?
They have the um the soluble fibers and
all these awesome things. All right.
Wonderful. Okay. Well,
flax flax foods are also
anti-cancer. You know why?
Because they have something called
lignens. Lgmins.
Lignens. Ah, that's awesome. Lignens
prevent cancer. Whoa, that's great. I
want some more lignens in my uh in my uh
my life, right? I want lignens. Well,
let me tell you something about
lignens. Lgnens are
phytoestrogens. Did you know
that lignens are also
phytoestrogens? That's why they fight
cancer because they're phytoestrogens.
You probably didn't know that. Anyway,
flax seeds
um they've been studied they've been
studied because they uh the effects of
flax seeds have been studied on
biomarkers of
tumors and uh urinary excretions uh of
lignens in postmenopausal patients newly
diagnosed with breast cancer. And the
researchers concluded that consumption
of flax seeds has the potential to
reduce tumor growth in breast cancer
patients probably because they're
phytoestrogens. Yeah. Awesome. So, let's
consume uh flax seed. In fact, I
actually recommend either flax seeds or
chia seeds or a combination of both. You
can go back and forth. one day flax
seeds, the other day chia, and just go
back and forth every day, whatever you
want. I do recommend them daily,
especially if you are well actually
daily all the time. Just period. Why?
Because most people don't eat enough
omega-3 fatty acids, just what it is.
Most people eat a excess of omega6 and
not enough omega-3. And we need
omega-3s. We just don't get enough. If
you eat an excess of omega-3 of
omega6, you're not converting these
omega-3s into longchain omega uh 3es.
These are short chain omega3s and you
need to reduce the amount of omega6 in
order to be able to convert these into
longchain. So try to not eat oils.
That's another reason why to not eat
oils because if you're not if you're not
reducing the oils, you're probably
consuming an excess of omega6. that will
not allow you to convert the short chain
omega3 fatty acids and the chia and the
flax into the DHA and EPA which are the
longchain omega-3 fatty acids that have
those anti-inflammatory effects that
prevent cancer, heart disease, diabetes,
etc. Okay, so daily, how much? One
tablespoon minimum. If you have
diabetes, heart disease, whatever else,
maybe one to two. If you have an
autoimmune disease, more. Maybe up to a
quarter a cup, possibly. Okay,
possibly. Okie dokie. How about nuts and
seeds? What do they do? They're amazing.
Nuts and seeds. I have to finish. I
better hurry. Okay. Nuts and seeds. What
do they do? A study of consumption of
nuts and seeds like walnuts, al almonds,
na, hazelnuts, pistachios. Okay. They
found that people who consume them two
or more times a week lower the risk of
pancreatic cancer, which is one of the
deadliest, you guys. Peanuts, which are
botanically not uh nuts or seeds.
They're actually a legume. I don't know
if you knew this, but nutritional the
nutritional properties because of the
amount of fats or whatever they have,
they're more like a nut. uh but they
also were included in the in these
studies and they found that actually
peanuts are very good actually they are
like third place if you will in their um
anti-cancer properties and they have
found that um they have respirator even
like the thing that sometimes we hear
like uh red grapes have um but they they
prevent colon cancer
um they uh have a role in the expression
of estrogen receptors
uh in to prevent malignant colon tissue
from
growing. They have all kinds of very
good things prevent
metastasis. So two or more times a week
in fact ideally every day. Okay. So
that's nuts and seeds. Next. Did you
know mushrooms? Oi, this one could be
sometimes controversial for some people.
People think some people think that we
should not eat mushrooms, but
honestly it's nowhere in the Bible or
spirit of privacy. Oh, I hope I don't
get in trouble. Oh, somebody asked me,
"What's your opinion on wild
strawberries, mulberries, mushrooms such
as turkey tall?" I have never heard of
turkey tall mushroom.
Blettes. We over here in Mountain. Well,
if it's not poisonous, it's probably
great. That's why I can tell you stay
away from poisonous mushrooms or those
that are magic magic mushrooms or you
know ones that uh have psychedelic
effects. But other than that uh
mushrooms have been found. Okay, I'll
tell you about mushrooms. Let me tell
you real quick about mushrooms. Okay,
mushrooms are wonderful. Even the
white but uh white mushrooms those have
been already have been found to have
chemoprotective agents that prevent
breast cancer um and other types of
cancer. So any any mushroom any mushroom
they've done u uh studies that have that
uh can prevent uh cancer the growth of
tumors in breast cancer patients for
instance um they have for instance they
showed that white mushrooms extract
reduce the uh tumor proliferation tumor
weight without affecting uh other
tissues. For instance, they have found
um that invivo anti-cancer activity of
white mushroom extract and its uh main
fatty acid components among other
mushrooms that have been studied that
have anti-cancer effect are shiakei
rishi antrodia confer which I don't know
what that is but I'm probably going to
look it up. I think it's a mushroom from
Taiwan. Uh but obviously there's other
vegetables so not just mushrooms. Okay.
So this particular study that I read
about mushroom said also mentioned other
vegetables that have phyitochemicals
that suppress the same enzyme that
mushroom suppresses. So the same enzyme
that mushroom acts upon other vegetables
act upon. And here are the other mush
the vegetables that the same study
mentioned which are bell peppers,
broccoli, carrot, celery, chives and
spinach. Cruciferous vegetables
obviously beets. So all Oh, and number
one is garlic. Garlic number one
vegetable that suppresses these enzymes
that cause cancer. Same ones as
mushrooms. But you know what? The
simplest mushrooms that you find in any
grocery store. You don't have to buy the
very fancy ones. See that? They just
want to sell you stuff. They just want
you to spend money. Just buy white
mushrooms. Uh what amount of greens?
What does the amount of greens look
like? What amount? Like a big salad.
a big salad or a green smoothie. Big
green smoothie. That's the amount.
Okay. Uh oh, I cannot forget to tell you
about seaweeds. Seaweeds are the
vegetables of the ocean. They have
anti-cancer properties. A study
published in a Japanese cancer research.
Of course, they have to be Japanese
because they love seaweed. Of course,
they got a study about them. Uh they
reported that uh just a type of seaweed
that's widely consumed so nothing out of
the ordinary just a very common seaweed
uh that was considered safe inexpensive
called
mabu has the potential to prevent human
breast cancer they study a lot of breast
cancer I guess over there it's very
common obviously in women so they
reported that uh this solution of macabu
had induced apoptosis there's that word
again you
program cell death and three types of
breast cancer and these effects were
more intense than those of
chemotherapeutic agent in other words
chemotherapy. Um in addition
um it was observed that no apoptosis in
normal human breast cells. So it didn't
affect the human breast cells just the
bat
cells. Uh, also they did a study with
seaweeds in here in the Bay Area and it
if you eat normal amounts of seaweed, it
does not risk your thyroid. Some people
are worried about too much seaweed can
affect your thyroid because of the
iodine. Okay. Well, don't eat too much.
Just eat normal amounts. Don't eat like
a whole pound of seaweed every day. Just
eat normal amounts. Moderate amounts of
seaweed and just maybe two or three
times a week instead of every day. maybe
the equivalent of one nori sheet per
day. One nori sheet per day, no more
than that. And you're fine. And you'll
get your
iodine not in excess, also not in
deficit. It's what you need. All right.
So, uh some authors consider seaweed as
disease preventtors and health promoters
because they help prevent cancer and
also other cons conditions associated
with metabolic syndrome.
Seaweed contains phytonutrients not
found in other foods such as some types
of fiber. One type of fiber called
algenate only found in seaweed no other
foods. Unique
keratenoids one called fuga fuccoantin.
unique
polysaccharides. I'm not going to
pronounce them too hard, but only found
in seaweeds and several defense
polyphenols that have anti-cancer
properties. And they're only found in
seaweeds. You're not going to find them
anywhere else. Ain't that amazing? Okay,
I'm not going to say you absolutely have
to eat them. But if you eat once in a
while see seaweed, seaweed salad for
instance, now you know. or nori sheets.
Buy the nori sheets and then you put
stuff in there, veggies, some avocado,
whatever, and roll them
up and make like a little burrito or
something, your own sushi. What do you
think about that? Okay, don't forget
having a strong immune system is how you
prevent cancer. So do all the things
that help you to have an immune system.
What helps you to have a strong immune
system? What do you think helps helps
you to have a strong immune system?
Obviously following all the eight
principles of
health, good diet, but
exercise. You can eat perfect diet and
not
exercising. What's that going to do?
And if you're not sleeping, if you're
not drinking
water, what's that going to
do? You can be have a perfect diet and
still not have good health. If you're
violating the laws of health, the other
laws of health. If you're sleeping four
hours a night, I don't care how perfect
your diet is. I really don't care how
perfect your diet is. You're still going
to get sick. I'm sorry.
That's just how it is, okay? If you're
not getting enough sunlight to produce
enough vitamin
D, you have your immune system's going
to
suffer. You need that vitamin D. Not too
much. If you're two hours out in the
sunlight, you're going to get too much
UV radiation that might cause
cancer. See how it works? Okay. Last
thing I'm going to mention is the
effects of fasting. Just I just think
it's remarkable because they have found
that
fasting actually
helps chemotherapy work better. It has a
selective effect on making cancer
cells more uh vulnerable to the
chemotherapy and radiation treatments
and protects normal
cells from the radiation and
chemotherapy treatment. So it helps
people going through chemotherapy and
radiation to not have the side effects
of those treatments.
And the people who didn't go through the
radiation and
chemotherapy the can the fasting but it
has to be at least I think longer
fasting not just 24 hours like maybe 48
to 72 hours of water fasting has a very
similar effect to chemotherapy. It
almost has the same effects on cancer
cells as chemotherapy. Now I'm not
saying skip the chemo. I can't tell you
that. I'm just saying people who
voluntarily didn't want to do the chemo
or couldn't do the chemo maybe for
whatever reason and they
fasted, they had a similar effect that
what chemotherapy could do. But if you
do the chemo and the fasting, it's
better than chemotherapy alone, which is
important to know. I think patients
should know. And actually, you can
actually read about this. There's a book
called Fasting for Cancer
um written by this uh researcher who
came up with something called the
fasting mimicking diet. It's kind of
expensive protocol. You can actually do
it. You can order the fasting mimicking
diet. It comes to your house like a box.
I don't work for them. I don't don't
think I work for them. It's kind of
expensive actually, but it's very good
and you can do it once a quarter or
whatever. It has the benefits of doing
the fasting without really fasting. It's
like a very low calorie, but it's
formulated to have the same effects as
fasting. So,
anyway, so this is what uh my husband is
doing. Oh, no, it's covered. Some of it
is covered, but I just wanted to let you
know that uh my husband refused the
cancer. I didn't tell him to refuse the
cancer. I actually wanted him to do the
cancer so they wouldn't blame me that I
made him refuse the cancer. Actually, I
said, you know, you should consider it
because I don't want to be blamed. but
he's like, "Nope." His chances of it
coming back without the chemo were not
that great anyway. So, he decided not to
have it. But he's doing a whole food
plant-based diet. He stopped eating
sugar. He was eating sugar. He was one
of those vegans who eats sugar and
chips. Well, he stopped. He did daily
juices for two
years. He made his own juice every
morning.
vegetables, no fruit. Uh because you do
concentrate the sugar of the fruit when
you make juice. So he made only
vegetables, only put vegetables. I made
him green smoothies for about 6 months
and turmeric shots for about 6 months.
After that, he started putting turmeric
in his own juice. He put garlic in his
juice, by the way. Garlic, number one,
anti-cancer vegetable. Not a lot because
otherwise you start smelling like it way
too much. So about, you know, maybe one
or two cloves of garlic. Salads. He did
not eat salads previous to this. Maybe
one
salad week. He eats his daily salad and
he still does it every single day. Thank
goodness. Broccoli sprouts. I, as I
said, I make them for him. He still eats
them every day.
This is still hard for him. Make sure
you buy organic. He's forgets. Okay. If
you're going to buy
organic. If you're only going to buy one
organic thing, okay? One organic fruit
or
vegetable, make sure it's
strawberries. Strawberries are the
number
one fruit or vegetable with the most
amount of chemicals and the most toxic
chemicals, I should say.
We I live right here, you know, the uh
central coast of California where they
grow like 90 some percent of the the
strawberries
and I could tell you those fields are
covered up with
plastic. Uh the rows of of strawberries
are covered up with plastic. Under those
plastic under that plastic is all the
chemicals are
concentrated and that stuff is very
poisonous. I if you're going to just
choose one fruit or vegetable to make
sure it's organic, I would say
strawberries. Just strawberries. Now,
you can look up the dirty 12 or
something is called dirty dozen. I don't
know what it's called. Dirty dozen, I
think, of the top high, you know, fruits
and vegetables that have the most
fertilizers and pesticides or something
like that. I don't know. Maybe pick the
top five and make sure those are always
organic or something. Top three,
whatever. But if it's one, I would say
vegetables. That's what I would choose.
And as I said before, other life factors
like the eight the new start principles.
All right. And I'm going to skip the
story of this lady. This if you want to
read it on your own, I would highly
recommend it. Her name is uh Ruth
Hydridge. And you can read her story.
Ruth Hydridge, Dr. Ruth Hydridge, PhD.
how she basically
um fought cancer with a plant-based diet
and she's in her 80s. She's gotten all
kinds of Oh, this is Dr. Lorraine Day.
That's another story of cancer going
away with plant-based diet. So, Ruth
Hydrickch and Lorraine Day, those good
stories, look them up. Okay, we'll
finish with this um with
this verse again. Exodus 15:26. If you
diligently heed the voice of the Lord
your God, and do what is right in his
sight, give ear to his commandments,
including the laws of health,
commandments, laws of health, and keep
all his statutes, I will put none of the
diseases on you which I have brought on
the Egyptians. For I am the
Lord who heals you. Who heals you? He is
our healer, our
savior. Thank you. We I want to thank
God every day for being our healer and
our savior. I want to give you one more
time my
uh my website
healthfortoday.net. As I said in the
beginning, I want to apologize if I
haven't responded to your messages
uh this week because it was terrible
week for work for work. But this week
will be much better. This is our last
week of our 10day
uh challenge at my work. I do 10day
challenges at work and uh and this
Sunday we'll do our checkup to see how
our participants were doing. So I am
excited about that. But if you have
questions, if you want to do the 10day
program, download it from my website
health4today.net is right there as you
see it on top. the Daniel challenge just
like Daniel. Maybe one day we should
organize one with this group, True
Health Tuesday. We should just do one.
Don't you think? I think we should.
Anyway, if you want to do one, let me
know. We should organize one maybe
online. True Health Tuesday 10day
challenge. If you have any questions,
uh I'm still here or else we'll finish.
Oh, by the way, here's a You can do a
banana split, you guys. Banana split.
Healthy banana split. If you want to
know the recipe, you have to download
it. It doesn't have ice cream. Is a
healthy version of a banana split. What
do you think? All right. If there's any
questions, um I can maybe answer one or
two because it's super
late. But otherwise, I'll finish with a
prayer cuz again, I forgot to pray in
the beginning like I do because I'm just
terrible. I'm not very good at this
still. But I will get
better. I will get better. I will
eventually learn how to do this right
and start with a prayer. I have to put
like a post-it note or something. I
don't know. All right, you guys. So, any
questions? If you have any questions,
put in the chat.
All right, any questions? Or if
not, we will end. Thank you for being
here, you guys. What goes in the green
smoothie? All right, I'll give you the
green smoothie. Anti-inflammatory green
smoothie. This I did not come up with
it. I saw it from Dr. uh Brooke Goldner,
who has a protocol for u inflammatory
autoimmune diseases. You might know her
already. If you don't, look her up. Dr.
Brooke Goldner. She 20 years ago or
something like that by now, I think she
had lupus and she came up, well, she
found out by accident that some fruit, I
think it was blueberries, had some
anti-inflammatory effect. She's a
doctor, medical doctor, and she's like,
"Whoa, how come I never heard of this?"
She started looking up more, you know,
foods that might be anti-inflammatory.
She found all kinds of fruits and
vegetables, whatever. Eventually, she's
like, "Okay, well, I need to change my
diet." And she basically went on a whole
food plant-based diet, but she needed to
include a lot of greens. So, how? At
first, she was eating gigantic salads,
but it was hard to eat like two big
salads a day. Like, how how am I going
to do this? So, eventually, she's like,
"Okay, I'm going to make a smoothie."
So, here's a smoothie. She takes here's
a like a blender jar, right? Okay.
Blender jar. threearters of it is
greens. And when I make the smoothie for
my uh participants, I'm like, don't just
like and all of a sudden it's full. No,
no, no. You've got to push them down.
Just she does this, too. She pushes them
down. So, it's like squishes them.
Three4ers of the uh jar of the blender,
right? Threearters of it is greens. It
doesn't have to be the same. In fact, I
recommend it being different all the
time. Okay? So, one day you might do
spinach or whatever. Don't do spinach
all the time. That would be too much
oxilates. You want to change it up.
Okay? One day kale. Maybe do like a
green h super green mix or whatever from
Costco. One of those mixes. Okay. So,
kale could be could be even spring mix
could have different like lettucees or
something like that. All right. So
greens, mix of greens, dark leafy, put
them in there. And the rest, so one
quarter could be fruits, whatever fruit
you like. It could be one fruit like
mango. It could be many fruits. Could be
berries of course, a little banana,
piece of banana, whatever you want. And
then you fill it up to however much
water, enough to blend. But if you want
it very liquidy, you put more water. You
can put it up to 3/4 water or half, you
know, depends on how thick you want it.
Now, if you are not used to green
smoothies and you want it a little bit
sweeter, you can put a couple dates, you
know, like, by the way, I found some
studies that at first I was kind of
worried about giving dates to my
participants because I'm like, I don't
want their blood sugars to go up and I
only one date, you guys. But then I
found some studies that dates actually
don't elevate blood sugar at all or too
much. So maybe you can put two dates,
three dates, depends. Okay, but not like
a whole pound of dates, obviously. Two
dates, maybe maybe a little bit of
stevia if you're okay with that. There's
actually green leaf stevia, like
actually powdered stevia. It's not a
extract. It's just the leaves that been
powdered up. You can actually grow the
stevia yourself anyway. put a little bit
of that or I don't know, honey, I guess
something like that.
Um, and blend it. Now, if you're going
to use it as a meal
replacement, then put more stuff. That's
not going to keep you, you know, like
from breakfast to lunch, you got to put
maybe some oats. I don't know, put some
tofu even if you need some food. Okay,
that's not enough uh to keep you for
one, you know, that's not enough for a
meal. So, put more. maybe a handful of
walnuts, something to add calories if
it's going to be a meal replacement. If
it's not a meal replacement, then the
vegetables, the fruit, it's enough. And
then you can She drinks the whole thing.
Not all at once. Maybe maybe divide it
up in two. Uh but she drinks the whole
thing in one day. That's for autoimmune
diseases. If you don't have an
autoimmune disease, you don't have to
drink it maybe all in one day. You can
save half for tomorrow. That's fine,
too. Okay. So, that's the green smoothie
uh recipe. All right. Uh do we need
soaked nuts? Better if they're soaked.
It starts the um the process of of the
germination, I guess, sprouting process.
So, it does change a little bit of the
composition of the nutrients, if you
will. And also if you're going to make
something with them, like if you're
going to make like a cashew cream or
whatever, it makes them softer. So it's
better if you soak them, but you don't
absolutely have to. It's a preference.
It does start the sprouting process. So
it does change a little bit of the
compositions better. All right. We don't
have soybeans here. We have kidney
beans, chickpeas, and broad beans. Well,
that's wonderful. All beans, legumes are
very, very good for you. They are the
number one source of fiber in the diet,
all beans in general. Um, so I recommend
them to I recommend them every day
honestly because of the are they're
great sources of protein. Even though
when you do the, you know, diabetes diet
or whatever, they say, "Oh, no, they're
carbs." Honestly, most of the carbs are
fiber. So, if you take that away, they
have actually a good amount of protein.
They do provide dietary proteins. And of
course they have carbs and they also
have fiber. So some of those carbs are
fibers. They are a good source of
protein. Okay.
Um and fiber soluble fibers. Those are
the fibers that help to maintain blood
sugars very stable throughout the day.
So they're excellent. If you're
diabetic, I recommend eating half a cup
per
meal. Okay. So all in fact, I recommend
a variety. So you're saying kidney
beans, chickpeas, broad beans. Yes, add
more lentils, fava beans, you know, just
eat a variety because the more variety
the better. You're getting different
nutrients. The more variety the better.
Does green smoothie have to be
organic better. If it's organic,
definitely. Yeah. The the more organic
the better. If you're not getting
organic, try to wash them as much as you
can. Wash them. even soak them a little
bit of maybe uh vinegar water and then
rinse them really well or a little bit
of salt water and then rinse them very
well. That removes a lot of the
chemicals. So yes, I would do that. If
not, grow them yourself. If you have a
little bit of, you know, land, a little
bit of a backyard or a balcony, even
grow them in pots, that could be done.
I've done it, you know. So, anything you
can grow is better than none. But if you
can't grow them at all at all at all
then and if you can't afford
organic some greens is better than no
greens at all wash them really well soak
them for 10 minutes in salt water and
then rinse them and that will and even
uh um baking soda. So vinegar, salt or
baking soda three things you can soak
them with but don't forget to rinse
them. Rinse them very well and that
eliminates
uh a lot of the chemicals in those
fruits or vegetables.
Okay, you guys, thank you once again.
Sorry to one hour and 27 minutes, but I
think we learned something. Put a one in
the chat if you learned something today
that you didn't know before. Did you
learn something? I hope you did. And I
want to tell you something.
Seriously, this is not just for
us. This is for sharing.
This is for helping others. What we
learn, we need to
give to
others. Make sure you give this blessing
to others. Take this message, spread it.
There's a one. Yay. Somebody learned
something. That's enough for me. Even
one person. Um, make sure that you give
this to others. Now, if you've learned
something, you've been blessed today,
make sure you bless others with it,
maybe give this link even, you can give
this link, but if you can be that
messenger, spread this to other people
so that other people learn that God has
given us these
foods. He put the medicine in the food,
you guys. The medicine is in the food.
We oh last thing before I pray we
actually have a conference called food
as medicine. It's for health care
providers mainly. So if you're a
healthcare provider we give cus and
cmemes for healthcare providers are
dietitians and nurses and doctors one
day uh 5.5 I think no 7.5 CMEs and C
cus. It's going to be in October. Uh but
it's also an online and anybody can do
it. It's not priced for great because
it's for doctors, but it's there's an
online version. The version is a little
bit uh lower. Um and it's eat for the
earth. No, no, no. It's food for
medicine. No, food for medicine
cruise.org if you're interested. It's
food for food for no food as medicine.
Sorry. Food asmed Santa Cruz.org.
And the CME are provided by Adventist
Health. CME
CEUS Food as Medicine Santa
Cruz.org. All
right, let's pray. Dear heavenly father,
thank you so much for this opportunity.
Thank you for helping us to learn about
you and the foods you have provided.
Thank you for putting the medicine in
the food. Thank you for helping us know
more about the blessings you have given
us through this message that uh can heal
us. Thank you for being our healer, our
savior. Help us to live this message and
then to spread it to others to help
others to get to know you as well as
their healer and their savior. be with
us the rest of today and
um thank you again for everything you
have given us. Thank you Jesus in Jesus
name.
Amen. Thank you once again for being
with us. We'll see you in two weeks.
Okay, next uh program is going to be
about food. Oh no, sugar. Is sugar a
poison? That's what I'm going to talk
about. Thank you again. We'll see you
next